Well, you write so beautifully about nature.
You've been writing for 22 years,
and you've written about all different kinds of nature.
You've written about mountains and rivers,
and you've written about time.
And what I want to
start off with is the sensitivity
that you've developed over time,
a sensitivity to be connected to this much larger world
that we live in, both in space and in time.
Where does that come from,
and how have you cultivated that?
Hard to reverse engineer an answer for that.
I grew up in mountains.
I think that's probably the first answer to that.
And mountains sensitize you, right?
They are intense spaces and places.
The light feels brighter.
The snow on the face feels sharper.
The air you breathe, you feel
it like a wire in your nose.
It runs down into your lungs.
And so everything,
kind of crackles and tingles in the mountains.
And also because they're dangerous places,
you have to be alert.
And being alert means risk assessment,
but it also means being open
as the kind of atoms of the world meet you.
So I sometimes say my heart is made of mountains
and always will be.
They're the beginning and the end of all natural scenery
as far as I'm concerned.
So from that, I think at some level, I learned,
and obsessed with it.
I think I learned from it,
that I have a very strong obsession
with rock and ice and water and light
and all the things that
flow through and build my work.
And also, I guess,
they kind of,
they war, they wore away the usual boundaries
and shells of the self,
and they continue to do that in me.
Tell me about that obsession with light.
So I was flying into New York the other night.
Yeah.
And it was sort of a dark,
kind of like very cloudy evening,
thick clouds. And we're kind of landing.
We climb up to the top of the mountain,
we go through the clouds yeah and we get
to the bottom of sunset time and there was this
blood orange light that was shining through the
clouds and it was marvelous it was magnificent
and i have my phone in my pocket to go take
a photo and i go i'm never gonna be able to capture
it good there's just no way yourself i stopped
myself i didn't take the photo and then i just
started grieving that i'm never gonna have the
words to describe how beautiful this color light
was and it's just gonna be in my memory fading
away every single day and i was like i wish i
could describe this but how did i do that has
it faded i don't know i can feel like i can't
explain it to you and it makes me sad it
was so beautiful well there was a there was a slaughter
in that sunset right it was sanguineous it was bloody
it was it was it was wild um language will
always be late for its subject when its subject is
light it will be it stands no chance
right nothing moves faster nothing is more allotropic nothing
shifts its textures its granulations its forms more
than light so i would say abandon the dream
of correspondence so language will never ever meet light
granite has no grammar so for me once you
reach the point where you
stop the futile questing after correspondence
like oh how can my language possibly meet
reproduce carry the thing i have just seen what
can't cause dusting and zich the thing in itself
you'll never do that so abandon it and then and
then you're you're no longer irritably questing
after that and feeling that you're falling short
instead lean into artifice so for me metaphor
which is fundamentally a distortion of the thing
aristotle defines it metaphor is like unlike
this so sort of matching one thing to another but
across time and space is one of the most beautiful
ways of evoking but not and this is a
verb i hate capturing nature we shouldn't dream of capturing
nature because then it becomes our captive
and then it prowls restlessly backwards and forwards
in its cage and it's not itself so is it
like i'm thinking of an impressionist painting yeah right i
think of a monet you know like you're like
you're like you're like you're like you're like you're like
he's not trying to capture the scene he's trying
to paint his impressions exactly of the scene the
representation of perception rather than the
thing itself and perception is always
multiply filtered it's highly
dynamic it's psychologically textured so
water i've spent a lot of time trying to think
about how to write water recently as i spent four
years writing this big river book and over and one
thing i came to realize is there is no single
grammar of the word water and i think that's
a really important thing to think about and i think
that's a really important thing to think about and i think
animacy right there is no one way to write water
there is an there is an obvious way to write
water there is an there is an obvious way to
write water which is to let language flow as river does
and and i i absolutely have enjoyed playing with
that so there are sentences in is a river alive
which go on for there's one that goes on for
two pages um there's one that's 515 words long and
i didn't catch that wow well and
the dash i so i'm a preposition obsessive
and a punctuation obsessive so the the dash the m
dash that long dash not the hyphen but the one
that that lives between words is to me is
such a beautiful fluid piece of punctuation i think it's
my favorite piece of punctuation where a full where
a full stop bangs down the hard end the
bookend to a sentence to a thought the dash is
liquid it it flows two ways both ways meaning can
move against the current eddie back up the line
and then it's a very fluid piece of punctuation
meaning can move against the current eddie back up the
line and then it's a very fluid piece of punctuation
sentence or flow down the sentence so looking
at how we as it were traffic control meaning
with it with with using the tiny
stuff the punctuation and the prepositions which is
something maybe we can come on to talk about
the the buys the widths the next twos the
aboves the belows all of those let's go into it
yeah okay well i i love to speak for prepositions
because they they they don't get listened to
enough so to give an example um i sometimes
um i sometimes talk about the ways in which i
i write with nature so i write with rivers or with
mountains like almost as a co-author exactly and
there the preposition is what makes the difference
because if i were to say to you oh i
i write about rivers that's different that's me speaking about
the river but writing with rivers preposition shifts
is is a new thing that's where the rivers
and i are co-thinking about the rivers and the
rivers are the same thing so i'm not saying that's
the same thing but i'm saying that's the way that
we write about rivers and the rivers are the same
thing so i'm not saying that's the way that we
write about rivers and the rivers are the same thing
and then there's a step beyond that which is
being written by river and there we've we've gone so
we've gone from about to buy and we've
gone metaphysically we've gone a huge distance whoa
and being i at the very end of these years
of river journey i i think i came to know briefly
and very consequentially what it meant to
be written by rivers does the word a
word a conduit feel right yes you become
a channel exactly a conduit is a lovely word
for it because it is a river word it's kind
of what rivers rivers are i mean water seeks a body
we're water bodies doesn't always it will always
find a container sometimes that's the banks of the
river sometimes it's a wetland sometimes it's a human
body in this case i felt very strongly that
that the river was was was almost creating language through
me as a conduit and i think that's what i'm
doing to use your excellent word hmm tell me more
about how you weaved in the flow and the rhythm of
rivers into your writing well so rhythm is
something i'm is i'm obsessive about many things
i'm an obsessive obsessive but so you've so far
heard me on prepositions you should come on how i
write sometimes i feel like it'd be a good show
for you to come on that's a great idea we can
wig out we can nerd out all right i'll set up
a time about this day so you know i'll have a chat
nice library background um yeah okay nerd to nerd
um rhythm so we we recognize rhythm as a function
of of of poetry you would that's something we
actively listen for when we meet a poem when we
read a poem we we hear it in our mind's
ear a poem we sound it even fiction i mean james
joyce's ulysses uh or uh finnegan's wake
deeply rhythmically alert texts but in non-fiction
i think partly because it has this weird name
non-fiction the thing that it isn't um like it
isn't fiction it isn't fiction that's that's the only
way we define it it's like what's why what
are the two kinds of books exactly there's fiction
and then there's and the stuff that's not fiction
not fiction right which i just find so
strange and and i think that almost subordinate relationship
with fiction that non-fiction has is one reason why
we don't expect it to be rhythmic let's say
or to or to be sound patterned
and rhythm and sound pattern is something that
i have been obsessed with from the very beginning
because they they work upon the mind the reader's
mind the reader's mind's ear in ways that are
different to propositional language they're not telling
you what to think they're not an argument
they're not a set of facts they're not
laying out propositions they're working on what heeney once
called the backwards and the abism of the mind i
think it means that they get they speak to deeper
down from the bottom of the mind because they've
been obsessed with the abism of the mind and they're
forms of knowing, like in the same sense
that rhythm, you know, when, if we're dancing,
if we, we, our brains are not rational,
rationally analyzing beat, our bodies are moving with
it in ways that are surprising and
pleasurable and, and, but are involved with knowledge
as well.
So, so rhythm, what does that
mean in terms of like nonfiction?
I've, so first lines, I probably spend longer
on first lines than, than, than, than whole
chapters and they get rewritten hundreds of times.
So this is the first line,
first line of a whole book.
So much happens when you meet
the first line of a whole book.
So is a river alive?
12,000 years ago, a river is born.
First line of the wild places.
The wind was rising, so I went to the wood.
So, or let's take that one.
Exactly.
So there's a, exactly.
We have, we have alliteration.
The wind, the wood, the wind, we, but we
also have, we have rhythm and there's also a puzzle.
Hold on.
The wind's rising, but why would you go
to a wood when the wind is rising?
Isn't that the last place you want to be?
It becomes a dangerous place.
And so I, you know how Hemingway sort of
wrote these, um, he played with these sort of flash
fictions long before flash fiction, because you
know, how, how much suspense or puzzlement
could you set up in
a single, in a single sentence?
Um, so very often I, I try
to test a first line like that.
12,000 years ago, a river is born.
A river is born.
What does that mean?
Is it born forever in time?
And why 12,000 years ago?
But also that one is less,
uh, less rhythmic, shall we say.
But it's more mysterious.
It's mysterious.
There's an ominousness about it.
Yeah.
Something, something happened 12,000 years ago.
Okay.
Wow.
We're about to go way back in time.
Way back in time.
Exactly.
And then, um, yeah, I think the next line is
at the foot of a hill on which flints lie
white as eyes, water rises for the first time
from a crack in the chalk, rises and flows,
rises and flows and on we, and on we go.
So flint, flints lie white as eyes.
We have the white and the eyes at the
foot of a hill and then rises, rises and flows,
rises and flows, picks up the sound of the eyes.
So already the sound patterning
starting to starting to happen.
And the reader's mind's ear, as I
keep referring to it, gets activated by that.
I think whether they know it or not, they
start to hear internal rhyme and it just makes
you kind of sit up.
Okay.
This is, I'm not, I'm not dealing
with a kind of fact book here.
I'm dealing with a, with, with a text
in which something other, other forms and forces are
going to be active here.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
Maybe you can help me ground this.
But I'm thinking about the different flows of rivers, right?
There's rapids.
Yep.
There's still waters.
We say still waters run deep.
And then there's rivers that,
that, that, that kind of meander.
There's straight rivers.
Yes.
Like there's every single flow
that you could get in writing.
I feel like you could
find a river equivalent for that.
Absolutely.
And that's why I think the, the idea
that river language is, is just fast language isn't,
isn't right.
So.
Like, it's just too slow and slow.
They pool.
They, they pause.
They, yeah, exactly.
So there's a bit, I, I remember trying to
work on, so I paddled this huge river, the
Muteshikau Ship with the Magpie River up
in Northeastern Quebec, and we were dropped in
by float plane.
And then we, we, we paddled out over,
and there's nothing like you get dropped, we got
dropped in at the head of this
lake, Lac Magpie that's 75 kilometers long.
That's like, is from my home to the
center of London, Canadian scale boggles my tiny
English mind.
And then the river has you and you follow the river through some
wild water all the way to the coast of the Gulf of St. Lawrence.
So there are so many, as you say, like kind
of forms and almost species of water in that 120 miles.
And so when I came to write about it, I realized that the
flat water, the lake water needed a different set of rhythms and tones.
And then the river, where the river was fast, that's where
the dashes came and the liquid language came and the speed came.
And I wanted the reader to feel what
I felt like when that river picked me up.
So tell me, how do you write speed?
Is it like short sentences? Is it fast sentences?
Like how do you write that? Like, is
that what it is? What do you do?
So I can give you an example. So we're cutting
into a sentence that is already half a page long.
And I am staring straight.
I look down into the hole at the wave's foot and
then I'm airborne and slammed into the hole headfirst and upside down.
I am exploded out of the boat on impact as
if hurled from an ejector seat down into the white hole.
And river is punching fingers up my nostrils and river
is ramming fist into my mouth and down my throat.
And I'm deep now, but the right way up.
So I grab handfuls of water and haul for the surface on
them as if they're holds on a cliff or rungs on a ladder.
But they dissolve under each grasp and I'm kicking out
and feel my feet bang against the rocks on the riverbed.
And one of them catches briefly.
And.
And so on and so on and so on.
So there's a couple of things there.
And, and is your friend, right?
And is the is the conjunction equivalent of the dash.
It just it tumbles and it tumbles and it tumbles.
It doesn't slow or stop or ask
you to establish primacy or hierarchy between clauses.
It just runs you on and, and, and, and.
And the clauses between the ands get
shorter and quicker and verbs become more active.
River. And I dropped the article there.
So it's not the river.
It's river rams fingers up my nostrils
and river rams fists down my throat.
And I'm calling and, and, and,
and, I mean, it's very simple, really.
It's a syntax of panic, of speed,
of rapidity in both senses of the word.
So kind of, kind of easy.
But when you read it, you yourself become breathless.
You can't, you don't know when to breathe.
And that's what it's like being
buried in a rapid like that.
Yeah.
Tell me about.
How, when you're out, the notes become, become books
because you start off and you write these little scribbles.
Yes.
Just little scribbles here, little scribbles there.
And you're not back to that word.
You're not trying to capture the experience.
It's just little script scribbles.
And then you go from
there and then there's another step.
And then there's just the
work of actually writing the book.
How does that happen?
Yeah.
Thank you.
It fascinates me.
It is alchemical.
It's quite mysterious.
It's also very laborious.
So just to break it down into stages then.
So because of the nature of the big books
I write, they often take between four and eight years.
They take many journeys.
There's a lot of field work where I'm meeting people.
I'm thinking with other people, with rivers, with mountains.
So on those, I have my phone.
But I prefer to use just these little notebooks.
And they're just about this size, about A6.
So they, they.
They bend, they stick in a pocket, whatever.
And into those, I'm just always pouring
what I sometimes call like qualia or qualia.
Like in the philosophy of mind,
those are just the phenomena of perception.
Subjective perception is broken down into qualia.
And by that, that's just
a grandiose name for saying stuff.
The bits, the bobs, the fluff, the
pebbles, the feathers that stick in my mind.
As it might be a fragment of conversation.
It might, but most often it's an image.
And there's a, there's a, yeah, there's a real line that I'll come
back to, which is about what happens to image between notebook and page.
But I'll cut, I'll come back to that.
And so the notebooks there, and I'm
just, they're so messy that it's fragments.
There's no continuity.
Sometimes I call them like mica, like shards of mica.
They, the stuff that glitters that, that goes in there.
Hmm.
Because you don't have time.
To sort of fully process this stuff when
you're having encounter with river or people or mountain.
Just got to get it down.
Got to get it down.
And then, and then not worry about it.
But, but that would be quite, you know, at the end of each day, I'll often, even if I'm 4,000 meters on a mountain or a hundred miles down a
river, I'll still tired, flick the head torch on in the tent and just lie there and just jot and jot and try and pull it out of the brain fresh.
Yeah.
And then I'll just sit there
and do a few hours open.
You know what I've been doing recently?
I just get a little piece of paper.
It's like maybe four inches by two
inches, like smaller than an index card.
Huh?
And I've just been writing down thoughts that I have during
the day with the goal of filling up the index card.
And I'm always amazed at how many thoughts I've
had that I didn't even realize that I had.
And if I kind of force myself to get that full index card on the
page, I'm like, oh my goodness, the number of interesting things that are actually happening here.
Yeah.
Maybe not even interesting.
The number of things, whatever, it could be junk is actually way more than I thought,
but I need to just sit with it and let the thoughts kind of arise and arise.
It needs space.
It needs time, stillness.
So the page in your
description becomes like a condensation surface.
So you have this sort of vapor that you've thought that
you've been working in and with, but almost invisibly because it's evaporated.
But then when the paper
then becomes the thing that condenses.
Yeah.
And I, I speak for paper pen and
paper do things that pixel and, and keyboard can't.
I re I really believe that.
What about more intimate?
What is it?
I think there's a, yeah, sometimes say they're kind of the
notes are what you flip fresh from the fresh from the fire.
Like they're hot and they're, they glow that ill th they're, they're
unformed in terms of ways that could be communicable to the reader.
I think that's what I would argue.
I think that's a great point.
I think that's, I think.
Yeah.
to other people.
Like nobody could read my notebooks
and follow a linear flow.
I looked at them, they seemed completely messy
and beyond comprehension.
Exactly, except to me.
So they're highly encrypted.
There's only one person who could possibly-
This is the original encryption.
It's bad handwriting.
Exactly.
WhatsApp end-to-end has nothing on my,
if anyone, yeah.
So then how do you
then turn a highly encrypted code,
readable, legible to only one person,
into a book that might be read by 100,000 people,
if you're fortunate?
And the answer is with a lot of work.
But the next stage is when I come home
from a big field trip,
I will have five, six, seven,
10 notebooks all rammed and crammed.
And sometimes I will literally pick up feathers
and bits of earth and leaf and stuff
and just stick them in the back of the notebook
just as more mnemonics.
Yeah.
But then comes the, and what happens at this stage
is I sit with the notebooks and I'll work through
page after page, and now
I am on screen and keyboard.
And there, this kind of filling out happens
because each of those little fragments to me
becomes the end of a thread of memory.
So that's the only bit you
can see is the tiny fragment
and you, but as you pull, pull, pull, pull.
Pull, pull.
Exactly.
Pull.
Exactly, and they just keep coming.
And so there-
My memory seems to be
able to kind of go back
into where the fragment was.
And then the whole scene
within which the fragment was jotted
sort of opens around it.
And I find that very exciting.
And I then kind of summon
that space as best I'm able
in language or make a connection with,
and now is when pattern
recognition starts to happen as well.
You start to see this interesting mycelium
of connections open up.
And, and this is where I'll just mention,
I'll just mention this Rilke line
and see what you think of it.
So it's in his letters to a young poet,
which I would say to any reader.
Gotta read it.
Any writer.
That's actually at,
it's on the main table at my house right now.
No way.
I've just been flipping through it.
Yeah, I was reading it last week.
Oh, that's beautiful.
Slender, wise, distilled, just fabulous.
Yeah, writer to writer as it were.
And he says, I don't know whose translation this is.
The images,
of the eyes are now present,
but now is the time to
go and do the heart work
on the images that lie inside you.
Something like that.
So I think what he's getting at there
is the distinction between that kind of immediate,
empirical sort of noticing.
The notebook, the notebook work is at some level,
the image of the eyes, but the heart work,
that's the really hard work.
The hard work is the hard work.
And that's what comes when you return
to these images and start to kind of understand
their relation to other parts,
to see how they've lodged in you,
to see how they resonate.
These, so that's the hard work.
Make that concrete for me.
What's an example?
Yeah, really, really good question.
So when I was writing a book called Underland,
which took me eight years,
I came to realize that
there was a series of images
that recurred across many of the journeys.
And one of those images was,
perhaps, the image of the eye.
Which is perhaps, unsurprisingly,
the image of the open hand.
I say unsurprisingly because the earliest cave art
is exactly, I don't know if
you know how those were made,
but-
I don't know anything about it.
Okay, so what you'll know if you summon them
into your mind's eye is that they're not hand prints.
So it's not that you get
a red print of the hand.
You get the outline of the hand.
And the way they,
the way it seems that the red print
that the early artists, cave artists did this,
they would take a mouthful
of red ochre dust, let's say,
and then they would place
the hand on the cave wall
and then they would blow the dust around it.
So in effect, they're creating a stencil.
Some of the earliest art is stencil art
with the human hand as the stencil.
So then you take the hand away,
you don't have the mark of the hand,
you have the mark of the absence of the hand.
And there's something very beautiful and ghostly about that,
that what we see is
not mark but absence of mark.
And I became obsessed with that and realized,
I'd see it in graffiti in the Paris catacombs,
like made using spray can 20 years earlier
rather than 36,000 years earlier,
but there was a commonality between those.
And I began to realize that the open hand
was part of a repertoire
of images that would become the heartwork of the book,
to use Rilke's term.
So what you're saying there is you see this image
of the hand and the absence of the hand,
you see it in Paris, you
see it in the old cave art,
and then you get to the keyboard, you say,
okay, there's something deeper going on here.
And then that is when you
begin to pull on the thread
to figure out what is that deeper thing.
And then to even go
back to earlier in our conversation,
that's when the work of impressionism
kind of comes into the writing or something.
Yeah, so it's sort of about pattern recognition.
Again, to use a phrase I used earlier,
and I don't teach writing very much
because I teach at Cambridge my whole time.
But when I do teach writing,
the first rule I give
would-be writers is ass on chair.
Turn up for work.
It hurts.
It's not much fun.
You feel like you're banging your head against a blackboard.
Don't run away from it.
Don't fetishize it.
Don't feel it's the working environment.
Don't think you have to get the angle,
the feng shui angle of your pencil
exactly right on the writing desk
before you can possibly begin to start writing.
Ass on chair.
Show up for work every
day and put the time in.
Second thing, look out for patterns.
And so the open hand,
I suddenly realized that the open hand
was recurring throughout my notebooks.
Include not just that kind of cave art hand placement,
but also the open hand of greeting,
of community, of welcome.
And so I began to find ways of just highlighting
the open hand wherever it occurred
in my journeys, in my writing.
And that then becomes a
sort of pattern that lights up
and for the reader and for the writer.
And that lighting up is exciting when it happens.
Yeah.
So as reading is river alive,
one of the things that
occurred to me is that there,
was a sense of awareness that you had a connection
with nature and attunement that
I think we lose as adults.
And you're talking to your son
and the conversation went something like,
I'm writing this book about is a river alive?
And your son said, duh, of course,
like that book's not gonna be very long.
And it made me realize like,
there's these things that kids know
that are facts about the world.
Obviously it's like that.
And then as adults, we lose that.
Exactly. And then as adults, we lose that.
And somehow when it comes to nature,
you haven't lost that.
Well, I think wonder is an essential survival skill.
Ooh, tell me about wonder.
Well, wonder is jaw dropped, right?
It's the moment where you are just stepped back
by the world's, by the miracle of the world
and the freely given miracle of the world, a rainbow.
A rainbow is like, I mean, a rainbow is,
I think when you see
a rainbow, you still stop and-
Of course.
Oh my goodness, the most magnificent rainbow.
I just stood there by the window.
I was like, wow.
Wow. How is that?
Every time, every time.
That's wonder.
And every time, rainbows are like,
they're the charismatic megafauna of wonder, right?
They do it often and well.
The other thing about a rainbow is it's utterly bespoke.
That is, it was your, it was David's rainbow.
It was no one else's
rainbow in the way it appeared.
It was not created to
you because it's a prismatic function
that the water is lensing light and separating light
into its constituent wavelengths.
But the precise nature of that color
and the position and form of
the rainbow in the sky is,
if you'd stepped a yard to the right
and become a different person,
you'd have seen a different rainbow.
So that's wondrous.
And science finesses the real into wonder.
Like science is, science doesn't mean unweaving the rainbow.
It can help us continue
to be astonished by the world,
just understand a little bit better how it works.
So I don't see science and
wonder as opposed, but I am.
I always struggled with that.
When I was a kid, I
used to tell my science teachers,
I don't want to know, I don't want to know.
Because for me, there was
a way that science was taught
that actually stripped the wonder out of the world.
And I didn't like science class
because I didn't want to know
about the stars in the sky.
I just wanted them to
be like little dots that God
or whatever hung in the sky.
And that was that, cool.
Well, you and John Keats, the poet who castigated science
for, as he put it, unweaving the rainbow.
So yeah, so you have
a friend in a romantic poet,
great, great author of Ode to a Nightingale
and Ode on a Grishna.
And so let's not unweave the rainbow.
Actually, I think unweaving the rainbow is part of the,
is fine, I'm fine with that.
But wonder is super powerful
and it's kids have it, right?
Not always, no, I mean, children,
but I sometimes call children wondernauts.
Like they're not astronauts, they're wondernauts.
They're continually voyaging in wonder.
So when I write for children,
I try to let wonder kind
of take charge as it were,
but also with an ear to rhythm and sound.
So I wrote a spell
in this big book of spells,
nature spells for children.
You wrote this?
Yeah, I wrote this called The Lost Words,
working with this wonderful artist called Jackie Morris.
And so I wrote, for example,
I wrote a spell for the otter.
And the idea is that children would speak these aloud
as spells, they would become spell casters
and they would kind of conjure back, you know,
the magic of the spell.
And then they would conjure back these creatures,
plants or birds.
So the otter spell begins, I'll
see if I can do it.
So, otter enters water without falter,
water supple slider out of halter into river.
This shape shift is a sheer breath taker,
a sure heart stopper,
but you'll never spot an actual otter,
only ever bubble scheme or shadow flutter.
And then it ends, run
to the river bank, otter dreamer,
slip your skin and change your matter,
slide your outer being into water and enter now
as otter without falter into river.
Nice, something like that.
So, but you can hear the, again,
the liquidity of the flow of the internal rhyme
and the otter and the language and such like.
So, I think that's it.
I think there's wonder, there's otter,
there's rhythm, there's pace.
That at least is what I'm trying to do.
And then watching children actually take those
and speak them aloud as I get these wonderful films
sent to me of children kind of on riverbanks,
speaking the otter spell and then like,
where's the otter, where's the otter?
Well, what you're talking about with wonder,
it reminded me of awe and
there's a poem by William Blake
and it starts like this.
It's like,
to see a world in a grain of sand
and heaven in a wildflower,
hold infinity in the palm of your hand
and eternity in an hour.
Yes.
Like, yes, yes, yes, yes, right?
Like to see a world in a grain of sand,
like there's a way of activating and awakening your mind
that, oh, it's just a grain of sand.
Come on, let's go on.
Versus like, it's a grain of sand.
Think of the lineage of that grain of sand,
how it got there.
And all the times that
the waves have come over it,
the feet that have touched that thing.
And like, just in a grain of sand,
the variance of what we can see
or not see can be so vast.
And I think if you're writing about nature,
that applies to everything, right?
Yeah, Blake's a wonderful example.
And he also says the
green tree is to some people
just the thing that stands in the way
and to others, it will set them weeping,
like this.
So again, it's that kind of,
it's the perception of perception as it were.
So yeah.
And the other thing about that,
say about that Blake poem is of course, it's tiny.
It is itself a grain of sand in that sense,
but it contains or speaks to eternity and universality.
So Blake's playing with scale there.
And I think when you realize that the human scale
are six foot bodies or whatever.
Thank you.
I'll take six feet.
Six feet.
You're welcome back anytime.
I'll lend you a couple of inches.
They're sort of how we measure and
see the world, but they're only one scale.
And in fact, we stand sort of
vertiginously above all of these extraordinary micro scales
and then the macro scales above us.
And that fascinates me.
There was this moment in the early 17th
century when the microscope and the telescope was
suddenly cracking open the scales of the world
and Galileo was seeing the mountains on the
moon and Anton van Leeuwenhoek was using a
microscope to peer into a droplet of pond
water and see it, as
he put it, teeming with animalcules.
Suddenly all these other scales of
life and structure were revealed through technology.
And technology is amazing at that.
But yes, as a writer, I'm often interested
in nesting different scales next to or within
one another.
Yeah.
The other thing I wanted to get at is the
blinders of rationality.
Oh, great phrase.
And you're right.
For those who, like me, have been largely
raised on rationalism, to imagine that a river
is alive in a way that exceeds the
sum of the lives it contains is difficult, counterintuitive
work.
It requires unlearning a process much harder than learning.
Yeah.
And the question is, what is unlearning?
How do we unlearn?
What is unlearning?
And that's what I was trying to get at
with the kids, that there's a way that kids see
reality more clearly.
Yeah.
More clearly than adults do.
But it's also enchanted.
Yes.
And it's filled with mystery and awe.
Yeah.
And that was one of the through lines of
stepping into the body of your work is like,
whoa, there's something there that I don't know
how to put words to, but it's sort of
a question to pursue, you know?
Thank you.
I see the universe as, or the universe
we inhabit as, how to put this, shattered by
mystery.
Yeah.
It's interesting to me, I think of
these early, you know, the early cave explorers,
the early cave painters, when you hold up a
light in a cave, especially if it's a flame
light rather than a torch light, you light up
just a tiny bit of the cave wall and you're
barely aware of the extent of it around you.
And as you move, the light follows
you but is only ever lighting up.
That's where we live.
I mean, rationalism, we think rationalism is
the great light that floods the universe
and tells us the secrets of everything.
Francis Bacon in 17th century says, let us
torment nature until she yields her secrets to us.
But nature's secrets far outstrip the tormenting tools
of rationalism. So I suppose I enter each
landscape, each encounter, each book aware that
there is no possibility of catching and
representing everything. So then it becomes a case of
what do you light up and also what mysteries
do you allude to, do you recognize? I mean, on the
river, I had this encounter at the end of this big,
big river journey, the end of four years of
river travel with something that I can only describe as
a kind of river being. It felt like
a very godlike presence. How does language even come
close to representing? That's the bit where I've
really, really struggled with the language. I've
really struggled with the language. I've really
felt I was being written by an
external force. So what happened? You were?
Well, we'd been traveling, you know, this hard
river journey for 10, 12 days. We'd been buried
by the river. The river was running really
high, huge wild river, that time of year, normally
running about 150 cubic meters a second at the
outflow. Here it was running 275. So it was like,
it was more than double its normal, or
it's approaching double its rate. And so we
every day we were we were tumbled, we were
we were swimming, we were bashed off rocks, we were
running huge six foot waves sometimes. And that just
wore us away. And each night we'd pitch camp
and we'd have to catch fish for dinner. And
you know, it was just just hard travel. But also,
metaphysically, it was kind of wearing me away. It
was unlearning me. And that is where we come
back to your question. The river did the unlearning
and it did it physically, but it also did it
metaphysically. And it said, well, I'm not going to be
able to do it. I'm going to have to do it.
And it said, well, I'm not going to be able to do it.
I'm not going to be able to do it. And it said, well,
what? What? What do you mean this? This is
just water. This is just dead matter. That's sort of
what the river was doing to me. It was
showing me its agency, its will, its presence, its force.
And, and a great deal changed for me in that,
in that time. And then at the very end, I just,
I think I described it as kind of these two auras
as it were my aura and the river's aura just sort
of overlapping and setting up a new kind of, you know,
a new kind of, you know, a new kind of, you
know, a new kind of, you know, a new kind of,
you know, a new kind of, you know, a new kind of,
an interference field for the first time and
becoming very, very aware of this, this thing
that has been moving through that landscape hugely
consequentially for again, 10 to 12,000 years. So,
and, and so I felt small, I felt one among
many kinds of being, and it was a, I suppose, a,
an experience of, of the divine,
of, of something like faith temporarily.
Visceral.
Visceral and mystic.
And utterly fascinating and changing forever. And
then, and then you're left with the question,
how do I, how do I find language to carry
that? And again, it doesn't have to carry it. It merely
needs to kind of register some, some analog
to what happened then, because you'll never carry that.
I think that another thing that you
do is you find these questions, these,
they're narrow questions, but they're expansive.
They're narrow questions, but they're expansive.
You know, there's the question from Jonas
Salk, who says, are we being good ancestors?
And then you ask, can a forest think? Does
a mountain remember? And then is a river alive?
Tell me about those questions.
Yeah. So the, the very first book I wrote in my
early to mid 20s was a book called Mountains of the Mind.
I grew up as a mountaineer and climber, as I mentioned, and the, that was a
book that, it was, like, it was a book that I kept going back and forth.
that began as a question. It's a very old
and famous question. Why climb mountains? And why do
we climb mountains? Why do I climb mountains?
George Mallory, who died on Everest in 1924,
famously responded in New York in 1922. When
asked, why are you climbing Everest? He said,
because it's there, which became this sort
of legendary answer, but actually gets us nowhere.
This does not help me at all.
No, exactly. You're right.
I'm like, I want to be like, wow, that's
profound. I don't think that helps me one bit.
It's a bit like my son saying
to Iza River, like, well, duh, yes.
Well, that one I feel like is
like, your son is just smack dab, right?
Okay, because it's there.
But the Everest guy, I'm like,
okay, you know what I mean?
Well, I hear you. It has become the
kind of most used answer to the question, well,
why do we climb mountains? But so the meta is-
Maybe the view is nice. It's challenging, but-
Yeah.
Yeah. Well, it took me 300 pages to
answer the question in A Mountain to the Mountain,
took me 300 in Iza River Alive, and I didn't come
to the end of any of them. But I think having that
puzzle, that enigma, the enigma wrapped in the mystery,
I think is a phrase for it. These are
deceptively simple questions. Why do you climb
a mountain? Because it's there. Iza River Alive,
yes. But no, actually, when you begin to ask them,
so they become, I don't know how to put it,
they become, let me give a caving
example. It's the portal. It's the narrow portal,
seemingly narrow portal. And once you can make your
way through it, dive the sump that it leads to,
and then you surface into this immense space.
And that is the space of complexity, of mystery,
of polyphony, of many voices. It's
crazy how much you see that
mythology, right? That's the closet in Narnia. You
walk through and you enter a whole new world.
There are so many examples of portals. So many.
And that's what they always are. They're narrow.
You step through the narrow gate and then
vast expansiveness on the other side.
The wardrobe that leads to the other
landscape, the bungalow you duck into and find
yourself in a cathedral. The portals fascinate me.
And actually, you've helped me to a really
useful crystallization of that, which is those questions
are portals. They're modest. They're the wardrobe.
They're the modest entrance point. And then you
push through the...
through the fur coats. Whoosh, you're into
it. And in fact, Mountains of the Mind,
you've reminded me, now begins with an image from
Narnia. The very first page has an image of
my grandma. Because I remember my grandmother's wardrobe
with her fur coats hanging in it up in
the mountains. And I would push through into
that, dreaming that I would step through into
a winter landscape. And then actually the mountains
helped me do that. So yeah, the questions are
portals. The other thing I should say I do at
the very start of a book, other than find the
question that is the portal, is I write myself
a letter. Whoa! My future self, a letter. And I,
because I know these books are going to take,
once I've committed to them, once I've found the portal
question, they're going to take me three, four,
five, six, seven, eight, eight years. I change
a lot in that time. The world changes a lot
in that time. The book, of course, will mutate and
metamorphose a lot in that time. So, so I tend
to write, I tend to write, you know, dear Rob,
the future Rob. And then in that letter, I try
to just say what I, what my heart hopes the book
will be, how I think it will be shaped,
what its resonances or key metaphors might be, where I'll,
where I want to go. And then eventually what I, what
I want it to do in the world. And they're all
tentative, right? I'm not, these are not,
it's not a set of commandments. There are
just, I'm not going to write a book that's going
to be a set of commandments. I'm going to write a
book that's going to be a set of rules. And then
I try to write a book that is more of a
clarification of how I'm feeling about the
book at that very, very, very early stage.
Then it's, what I love is looking back at
those letters when I finished the book and, and seeing
the relationship. And sometimes it's hugely
discrepant and other times it's surprisingly
close.
So with those questions, do you like hang
them on your desk? Is that, because here for,
always that kind of explicit and concrete?
I'm trying to think I, so I, I don't pin
questions on my desk, but I do pin, put quotes.
So for example, on this, with this book, there's
this amazing line from Ursula Le Guin that she
wrote very late in her
life. And she says something like,
I think it's right before the first chapter after
the prologue. And if you just want to read it.
Correct. Let me read it.
I think that's where it is.
One way to stop seeing trees or
rivers or hills only as natural resource is
to class them as fellow beings, kinfolk. I guess
I'm trying to subjectify the universe because
look where objectifying it has gotten us.
哼
to subjectify is not
necessarily to co-opt, colonize, exploit.
And this is the bit that I really focused on.
Rather, it may involve a great reach outward
of mind and imagination.
Yeah, it ends strongly.
A great reach outward of mind and imagination.
Exactly.
And that helps us think back to the portal.
So the question seems simple,
the key that unlocks the door,
but actually the real work is,
because to really answer yes,
if you're not a nine-year-old,
to the question, is a river alive?
Those of us raised on rationalism,
it requires a great reach outward of mind and imagination.
So Le Guin helped me keep thinking,
I have to keep reaching,
I have to keep reaching outward.
Sorry, there's so much that
was just like washed on me.
It's almost hard to like,
I don't even know where to ask.
The river.
I don't even know what to ask.
The river's going.
How much of writing a
book for you is an adventure
versus like a plan?
Actually, maybe we'll just follow a river analogy.
Like say that you're whitewater rafting.
Like there's, we're going to go
from point A to point B,
but how you're going to get
there is going to be nuts.
And hopefully you make it there, right?
Yeah.
Where does that analogy break down?
Where does it hold up?
So with the river book more than any other book,
I felt torrented.
Yeah.
From the beginning.
We'll stay with the metaphor.
But actually I felt rather than rafting downstream,
I was walking upstream.
You know when you're, when you walk in a river?
Yeah.
And you feel the muscles of that thing, right?
A river is a, it's a powerful presence physically.
And it's unceasing, it's relentless.
Exactly.
It's just push, push, push, push, push, push, pressure.
And one thing I've found from physically walking in rivers,
which I do quite a
lot, because they make great paths,
especially where the forest is thick on either side,
is that when you have your feet planted you're fine.
The river's not going to push you anywhere.
It's when you have to
lift a foot to make progress.
So one foot comes up and
then you're only on one foot
and the river is pushing you off balance.
So actually it's stepping forwards.
It's the act of walking that unbalances you.
Writing a book is, is
like walking upstream in a river.
You can get to a point, stabilize yourself,
but when you come to take
the next step, you lift that foot,
that's when river knocks you off balance.
It's also really exciting,
and that's how you make progress.
But I found very strongly
that the river was also showing me the direction.
I didn't need to worry about direction.
It felt very intuitive,
but each step was because the
force of the flow of ideas
and people and encounters and rivers themselves
was so strong, it was unbalancing, torrenting
in fascinating, but not always easy ways.
You've been talking a lot
about your relationship with rivers,
and what is your relationship with other people
in the book writing process?
We sort of got it actually
with that Ursula Le Guin quote,
where you get other writers
who are almost giving you seeds,
and then you can basically take those seeds
and turn them into something else.
What about peers?
How does that show up in your writing?
Such a smart question.
And they are themselves kind of river presences,
I guess. Yeah.
I think a person is not
a fixed and sealed thing, right?
We know this.
We are all in motion
and changing all of the time.
We're all in flux.
And so, but I love people.
You know, a lot of
nature writing, a phrase I hate,
but a lot of nature
writing used to be thought of
as kind of almost people-less.
It was only about the land, as it were.
But- I mean, John Muir,
I don't think of people
whenever I think of his writing.
I always think of the mountains and stuff like that.
Right, right.
But Muir very shabbily treats
and sort of discards the
native presence in those landscapes.
So particularly in his early work,
when what he calls Indians
come into view in the landscape,
he will kind of shuffle them off.
He will frame them out.
Wow.
So, and I have come to love writing about people.
And it's partly that I hang out with,
I try and get myself to try and get myself
to travel with people who fascinate me.
It's back to being an obsessive obsessive.
And almost all the people who fascinate me
are people who are themselves fascinated by stuff.
Obsessive obsessive, specialist specialist.
So for example, Giuliana Verci,
this Chilean Italian field mycologist,
mushroom fungi specialist who I traveled with in Ecuador.
She's one of the most amazing people I've ever met.
And she can hear fungi.
She's a dowser.
She can sense buried water.
She can tell you flow rates.
She's like has an astonishing sensitivity to water.
And that's, I think,
inseparable from her sensitivity to fungi.
I was traveling with her in this cloud forest
trying to find, make second collections
of two new species of psilocybe,
of magic mushroom, as we might call them.
And she could hear them before she could see them.
She could sense them around three bends in the path.
And I know you're as puzzled as anyone else.
I've told this story too,
but I watched it happen once.
And I was there when it happened a second time.
She just sort of says,
ah, I think they're near now.
We were two more turns
in the path and then woohoo,
which is what she calls when she sees a fungus.
And she's down and there.
One specimen in each case,
single fungi in a huge cloud forest.
And I should say,
she's a serious, hardcore field scientist, right?
She's written the field guides to
the, you know, a, you know,
fungi of Chile.
So we're not talking about a kind of, you know,
crystal swinging mystic.
I mean, she's hardcore scientist.
She's, but she goes about things a different way.
So how do you write someone like that?
In a way, it's the easiest thing.
You just transcribe them, right?
Their speech is incredible.
Their way of being in the world is incredible.
I love it when, and I
found it particularly with this book,
people talk about them as characters.
So it sounds like this is a novel.
It isn't a novel,
but they are characters.
They're incredible, incredible characters.
So the books are filled with dialogue because,
but it's true dialogue as it were,
best fit true dialogue.
Yeah, there's a poet I like,
his name's John O'Donohue.
Oh, yeah.
And he has this line.
He says, when was the
last time you had a conversation?
A conversation that wasn't just two intersecting monologues,
but a conversation where both people found something
within each other,
within themselves that they didn't even know that they knew.
And the way that I imagine that is like,
you're kind of building a fire in conversation.
Like what we're doing right now,
it's like, I can't do this on my own.
You can't do this on your own.
We're in this together now.
We're actually creating,
we're in a process of co-creation.
And that's what conversation is.
And he talks about that.
And the last line is so beautiful.
He says, conversations like that are food
and drink for the soul.
It is like, wow.
And all this is the same, the writing process,
when you're with somebody, like, oh, I'm gonna do this.
I'm gonna do this.
I'm gonna do that.
And then you're with somebody like that woman
or your friend who you go kayaking with.
There's probably things that can get into your book
that you would never be
able to get on your own.
And they're almost a kind of co-writer for you.
Absolutely.
I love your idea of building a fire together.
I think that's,
I actually almost prefer that to John O'Donohue's metaphor,
food and drink for the soul.
Though O'Donohue, it's fascinating how many people his,
cause he was sort of a quiet writer.
And, but I have so many conversations with him.
And I think there's so many conversations like this,
where there's one line or a poem or something,
and it just lights people up.
Tell me about poetry.
Like you learned poetry as a kid.
And also one of the things
that we sort of talked about before,
but it's how rhythm, sound, and tempo,
they can kind of move you as a reader
in ways that exceed the actual prose itself.
And that's what poetry does.
It's almost more than the words, but it's implicit.
And I think this is
why you have to memorize it.
And I think that's why you have to memorize poetry
because it's only once it
begins to be known by heart,
we say, right?
Once you know it by heart,
then you begin to see all the rhythms and they,
it's almost like a flower.
Like it takes a while to
bloom, but once it does, wow, it,
huh, I didn't know it could do that.
Exactly.
The blooming is a lovely image for it.
It's entered you and then the seed is sown
and then the blossom comes.
And I mean, the last 10 years,
I've been lucky to collaborate with artists,
with, so I've written libretti for full length choral works.
I've also written a bunch of albums
and actually I have to say songwriting,
writing lyrics has become,
I think all of these have helped me with,
with Is a River Alive.
I think that's the book that
I've spent the last 22 years
learning to write and particularly the last 10,
because actually writing lyrics,
writing libretti, writing poetry.
You wrote a requiem, right?
Written a full length requiem.
I'm like, yeah, that's going
to be like a 75 minute
huge choral work.
It's going to premiere in Helsinki.
So can we do this?
Can we just go through
libretti and then all of them?
I just want to hear kind of quickly,
like what those forms have taught you about.
As a long form writer.
Yeah, exactly.
So we'll start with libretti.
What did that teach you as a long form writer?
Well, so I've written for opera.
I've written for, we created an improvised jazz opera.
That was about 15 years ago,
which we performed in a former nuclear weapons testing site,
which was very cool.
And so I expected to hear,
but the most recent one,
the one I've just finished is called the world tree.
Okay.
And it's about this.
Did you follow the story of the felling
of the Sycamore gap tree in the UK?
It was chopped down in the
middle of the night by two men
who just wanted to visit harm upon it.
It was a completely iconic tree on Hadrian's wall.
It featured in Robin Hood, Prince thieves.
Anyway, it was a huge national
and indeed international thing.
And it was,
so it's about it's a
deep history of forests and trees
and people in the north,
in the Northern parts of the Northern hemisphere,
it's called the world tree.
But what did I learn from that?
Well, writing for voice, especially for multiple voices,
you have to work so closely on,
for example, just the way one word transitions into another.
So if you have a glottal stop,
like at the end of one word,
that the singer then has to
overcome to flow into the next word.
That's fine if it comes
at the end of a line,
but if it comes in the middle of
a phrase or a thought, it doesn't work.
So you begin to think about the
sound currents of single phrases and the singability,
and that is not something as
a writer you would quite think about.
But in writing song lyrics,
the single thing that that has
taught me most clearly is to
let images lapse into looseness with one another.
Let me put it like that.
By that I mean as a
teacher at Cambridge, as a prose writer,
I'm basically a control freak.
I have to make meaning mean
exactly what I want it to mean.
So you work with syntax in all of these really,
really knotty,
complex ways to carry meaning.
So I wrote a song called
Uncanny Valley with my friend Johnny,
Johnny Flynn.
It's a really, it was so we
all got lost in the uncanny valley,
took a wrong turn at the end of the alley.
No one had a map and no
one kept tally in the uncanny valley,
in the uncanny valley.
And so when you speak it,
it sounds almost like a nursery rhyme and I'd
be embarrassed if I'd written that flat for the page.
But when you sing it and set it to beat,
and Johnny immediately looked at that and he said,
I want to set this off beat.
So when you hear the language and the guitar backing,
they sit slightly in friction with one
another and that gives it this uncanny,
off kilter, slightly strange.
And from the beginning, everything is off balance.
So they're letting language lapse into looseness,
letting images live,
live with one another in ways that
they start to cross pollinate in weird ways.
The other thing with that,
that I always love talking to artists about is the ways that serious artists are
conscious of things that are below the register of consciousness for the consumer of that work.
Like those things are talking about,
I would have never thought about those things.
I could probably listen to uncanny
valley a hundred times and be like,
maybe I'd get to,
wow,
there's something uncanny about the song.
But what you're saying is this is why that's happening.
Is that sort of the
puzzle pieces aren't quite matching up.
And that is a feature,
not a bug,
a feature,
not a bug.
Exactly.
What seems like a glitch is precisely the point.
This is a song about glitch.
And,
uh,
and,
and then I kind of carried that over to,
I mean the biggest glitch as it were glitch.
Glitch is such a cool word.
It's such a cool word.
It's such a cool thing.
It's where,
it's where,
where everything starts to kind of
vibrate and the hologram flickers and
reality is doing strange things and
rationalisms limits start to be met.
And the biggest glitch in the matrix
I've ever known was the encounter with
this river being.
And so there you have to
start to find ways that language can,
can glitch itself.
So again,
something I learned in songwriting carries over in,
in,
into the,
into the big books and then poetry.
Yeah.
Poetry.
So I,
uh,
mostly for children,
but here's a,
here's a glitch poem for you actually.
So,
uh,
a ran this beautiful,
quick little bird that moves so fast.
You can barely see it.
So when Ren was from stone to furs,
the world around her blurs for Ren is quick.
So quick,
she blurs the air through which she flows.
But,
but,
so there it's all about the glitch really.
It's about speed and then,
and then,
and then glitch because the rent is so quick,
she seems to pass out of sight.
She seems to glitch.
We gotta talk about words.
We have been,
we gotta talk about words.
No,
no,
no.
Now we're really gonna talk about words.
So tell me about place words.
Oh yeah.
Like how you've collected place words for terrain elements,
light life,
place names.
Yeah.
Top of them.
Now we're really gonna talk about,
all right,
well,
let's get some words going the on a master con,
um,
the,
uh,
the top of them.
So top of them is a place
name on a master con is a,
like a,
a gathering of,
of,
of words,
particularly for places,
obviously glossary lexicon.
So all of my books have,
have glossaries.
Um,
I'll give you a,
I'll give you a few,
I'll give you a choice
view from the glossary of not,
not because I want,
I want people,
I don't use big words because
I want people to think I'm a
big word user.
I use them because they are fantastically precise,
descriptive,
precise.
And I think precision is a function of,
of lyricism.
Yes.
So,
um,
so these,
so here's,
here's a few from the,
um,
uh,
from the glossary of is a river alive.
Um,
some,
a pit or pool into which waste liquids are drained,
a cesspit super void in astronomy,
a very large part of the universe
containing very little or no known condensed
matter,
galaxies,
super clusters,
et cetera.
I have a cool one.
Go on then.
Runak moon.
Oh,
runic moon.
And you pronounced it pretty well.
That's because I,
uh,
I literally went to Google and I was like,
I'm not gonna be able to pronounce this.
So I'm going to get the
actual pronunciation on my piece of paper.
So I practiced that.
You did good job.
So you're talking about precise the
shadows cast on the Moreland by clouds
moving across the sky on a bright and windy day.
Yeah.
Runic mum.
Exactly.
What's that four syllables,
but there it takes us in English,
a paragraph,
really a long sentence to,
to,
to describe.
So this,
I should say,
this is from Gaelic,
Scott,
Scott's Gaelic.
Um,
and it specifically it's from the Western
Isles dialect as it was sort of,
um,
idiolect of,
of Scott.
Well,
what I would imagine is as much as anything,
the language of nature is really
diverse as you move around the diverse.
Exactly.
Yeah.
I spent a wonderful two,
two and a half years collecting.
So I was raiding old glossaries,
um,
in,
in libraries,
regional libraries,
because in the 19th century,
a lot of people were making these dialect
glossaries and looking always for words for water,
for land,
for weather,
for forests and trees,
for,
for more,
for mountain words of relation with place,
precise,
lyrical,
fascinating,
strange,
sometimes absurd.
Um,
and I would also go and
interview language keepers as it were.
What are language keepers?
Well,
so there's,
I guess the elders of their communities,
especially where languages are threatened.
So Scott's Gaelic,
it's got as low as sort of 53,000,
speakers.
Uh,
it's starting to bump back up a bit now,
but it's highly regionally specific.
So I came to know an amazing man
to whom the book is dedicated called Finley McLeod.
And Finley was a language key first language Gaelic speaker,
but bilingual in English.
Um,
and he had made part of his remarkable life's work,
get gathering the language together and recording
it because a lot of it's oral culture.
Like you wouldn't necessarily think
to write down the specific,
um,
but so he handed me a,
this amazing document of Pete glossary,
which was like 150 words for aspects
of Moreland and Pete on Lewis alone.
And I just like,
wow.
And that's where I met for the first time.
Tell me about language death.
Yes,
it happens.
River death happens.
Language death happens.
I mean,
language death is very simple to,
to define.
It's where the last living speaker of a language dies.
And then the language survives.
And then the language dies.
Language survives in,
in recordings in a virtual record in paper record,
of course,
but it's,
it's no longer being passed on.
That's language death.
And when a language dies,
knowledge goes with it because
language is a knowledge storage system.
And when you,
and some,
some aspects of that knowledge cannot
be translated across into another language.
They're not alienable from the language itself.
So language death is a
kind of biocultural collapse as well.
A deletion of,
of,
of knowledge,
often that's been born and carried over many,
many generations.
Mm-hmm.
I asked you earlier about getting the early
notes and then we sort of talked about revision,
but I know every single sentence gets revised 20,
a hundred times.
Like tell me about the revision process.
How do you take something that
is eh and turn it into yeah.
Well,
I don't know if I do turn it into yeah,
but it,
I definitely try and move it away from eh.
And I am such a,
I'm a muddy,
mucky,
messy writer.
So I sometimes liken it to potting,
like being a potter and the,
you know,
in potting where you,
your first thing you do is you,
you have your bucket of clay and you reach down,
take a huge wet handful of clay and then yeah,
down it goes on the wheel.
And then the next bit is the hard work.
It's like the treadling,
I think they call it.
So you're sort of pumping that foot
treadle and that begins to spin the plate.
And then,
and then the work,
the,
the fine work begins,
which is where you begin to shape the bowl
and shape the bowl and shape the pot or whatever.
And then eventually once you've got that form,
then you start to do
all the ornamenting and so on.
But it is messy work.
I am not a writer who has
to finish one sentence before he goes on,
he or she goes on to the next.
And a piece of advice perhaps I would have for,
I often give this to writers
who are stuck with a block.
Like I can't begin the book
or I can't proceed with the book.
I'm like,
don't worry about that.
Just,
just leave it.
Actually,
I have two pieces of advice.
Let me give this.
So the first is when you end a day's writing,
Lee,
make sure you know what the
next sentence is going to be.
So when you wake up the next morning,
yeah,
you're like,
I'll finish that.
And that just gives you that little bit.
It's like pushing off on the bike and then,
and then you're cycling.
Good analogy.
So,
um,
so that's like the hook and I,
and,
and the other is like,
if you really stuck,
don't worry,
just go downstream,
jump into the book further
down and just write that bit.
And sometimes,
and I build my books out
of bits like there's sort of mosaics.
So I write them often very non-linearly.
I'll be like,
okay,
I know what's going to happen in that
paragraph or that scene or that bit of the
river or that,
that journey of that encounter.
So I'll write that as a set piece
and I'll be doing that with a hundred set
pieces,
even as I'm trying to kind of remember the flow.
So I'm not at all scared of,
um,
distraction,
uh,
discrepancies,
discrepancy,
diversion.
It doesn't have to be this beautiful linear writing.
I don't know how Richard powers writes.
I know Alan Hollinghurst,
the English novelist won the
book prize and many other things.
He writes perfect linear flow,
handwritten sentences.
He'll write a page a day.
He wants,
I once heard him say,
then he'll stop.
And then I write the next page the next day.
And then I'll stop.
If you write 365 pages a year,
you've got yourself a novel really quick.
That is an anointed human being.
That sounds,
that's exactly,
that is,
that is rare.
Well,
I think it must be,
and I am the opposite.
I'm like,
okay,
mosaic tile here.
Then do you like writing?
Yes.
I mean,
it is not coal mining.
It's yeah.
I think writers can really
whine about how hard writing is.
And at some level,
I think we need to recognize that you're sitting
on the whole comfortably behind a desk and yes,
there are external pressures and
maybe worried about financial circumstances.
I mean,
I think there's a lot of pressure in writing,
but there are also circumstances or deadlines or family.
You know,
we're all,
we're all under,
under many kinds of,
of pressure,
but the,
the actual writing work,
it,
it can be a bit hurty.
Let's say it's like it's brain hurting.
You don't want to do it because it's,
it's hard.
It's a natural.
Yeah.
Well,
it's,
to me,
it's pretty naturalized now after 20 years.
Okay.
It takes 20 years.
I actually feel vindicated.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's totally natural.
Just takes 20 years.
You're,
you've,
you've been writing,
I mean,
really writing how long,
10 years now.
Yeah.
Okay.
You just got another 10 to do,
and then it'll be fine.
It'll be like freewheeling on a
bike with no hands on the handlebars.
Great.
I'll be doing it like a,
like a guy in a hammock.
Well,
it,
it doesn't still feel like that,
but it's,
we're back to ass on chair.
It's like,
just show up.
And even if you,
even if you only get a paragraph that day,
your book's a paragraph longer.
How do you feel about using
your book as a way to,
to,
I mean,
I,
I don't.
Yeah.
Uh,
and
I cannot ever imagine doing so.
The only AI I use,
although I do try and switch it off is,
is obviously like spellcheck,
you know,
you get the,
the red and that is a kind of AI.
And I suppose it's been,
it's been scrutinizing us for a long time,
but actually I am because my writing skills are pretty,
you know,
often is highly violating of grammatical
norms. The grammar check goes wild.
He doesn't like it.
Does not like it. And I'm like, good, this
is excellent. I could give you an example of what,
as it were, Grammarly does not like. So
I sometimes like to remove verbs from sentences,
leaving them technically not sentences. But this is
seeing this huge Canadian river for the first
time from the sky. My first sight of
the river itself catches my breath. New paragraph.
A world snake in the green. New paragraph.
Cliffs dropping near sheer to water. New paragraph.
House-sized boulders on the banks. Time
falls from the rock faces above.
New paragraph. Water, blue, black, and
glossy in the deeper, calmer runs.
Peep round where it's stretched towards
and away from rapids, churning green,
gold, and gold.
And cream in the falls. End
paragraph. So that's five paragraphs, five sentences.
Sounds doing weird stuff. Cliffs
dropping near sheer to water.
And Grammarly does not approve, which I
take to be a badge of success.
It's sort of the paradox of Grammarly
that it makes the average piece of writing,
I think, much better. But it hurts
a kind of right... It
takes away from distinctiveness and individuality
that underlies so much great writing. I
think that's so well put, and I like
the idea of it hurting that. I think that's
a good way of putting it. Salman Rushdie yesterday,
I think, said, writers have nothing to fear from
AI until it can do comedy. And I thought
that was an interesting idea. Like the hardest thing
of all is to make us laugh. But I think
writing broadly does have a lot to fear from
AI, and we should resist it, including the absolute
piracy of our books that we now
know large language model composers have been undertaking
for years now, and feeding, absolutely feeding
them without any kind of recompense or licensing
or permission sought into the creation of
LLMs. I want to hear more about
what you do to make something feel visceral. Like,
I've been thinking a lot about that word, visceral.
Yeah.
And you talk about claustrophobia.
Yes.
And the way that that can feel visceral. There's
a line from William Golding where he talks about
sympathetic kinesthesia, twitching limbs,
rising heart rates, faster breathing,
like, and that we can actually experience
something vicariously. So early on in the
conversation, we're talking about
not trying to capture something.
Yes.
But this isn't the opposite, but it's actually
making the reader feel what you felt and having
Yes.
that feeling.
feeling feel vivid.
Yes.
Transferring that.
Wow. Well, yes. So visceral from, as it were,
viscera from the guts. Like, how do you make a
reader feel it in the guts? And I mean,
curiously, this is where feelings of nerves, you know, we
talk about butterflies in the stomach. We feel
that kind of characteristic tingles, anxiety or panic.
Underland, which is the book I wrote about,
which is highly kind of claustrophobic in many ways,
although it's also about the immense, immensities of the
underworld and the ways they open us up as
well as close us down. But there is a
passage in that where I am crawling through the Paris
catacombs. And I would say that the area under
your chair and between the legs of your chair,
So about a foot.
is considerably bigger than the pa- I mean, it
re- the affordance of this passage was so tight
that my nose, the back of my head was on
the base and that my nose was on the top.
Oh my goodness.
And I had to hook my rucksack to my
ankle and drag. And then the only way I could,
you could kind of move was just like
worm-like moving your way under. And then this,
this shuddering started, this vibrating stuff that we
were in, it was a rock passage, limestone. And,
and I came to realize, and the whole
ceiling was, everything was judging and the vibrations
were passing through the rock, through my body and back
into the rock. It was a train. It was a,
it was a tube train. We were under Paris. So
it was a Metro train. And I realized it was passing,
directly overhead of a, of a, and I mean, that
probably was the time I felt most afraid in eight
years of, of, of the Underland. Anyway, the roof
didn't collapse. We made it through, but so many
people have stopped reading at that point. I've
had, must've had a hundred people in readings and
talks come up to me and said, I loved Underland, but
when I got to that bit, too much, I just had
to stop. I had to jump. I had to jump
ahead. I was fascinated by this because being able to
vicariously affect your reading,
Yeah.
not their mind, but being able to make
them kind of clench, make their heart beat,
beat raise, make them go outside under a clear
blue sky so they can recover from the claustrophobia,
even though they were reading it in a
room like this. That's power. It's power and it's
fascinating. And I, I came to
realize claustrophobia is much more vicariously
powerful than vertigo and vertigo is quite powerful.
So when I'd written a lot about vertigo,
you know, people are like, oh yeah, I felt,
I felt a version of that. But with claustrophobia,
people are like, I had to stop
reading this. So it's just, yeah, sympathetic
kinesthesia is where you're affecting not mind, but,
but body, body and then mind. And it's a,
it's a, it's a fascinating power.
Worst claustrophobia I ever had was my first
MRI. I didn't really know what an MRI was.
Yeah.
And I just showed up and it was horrible.
You got it. You felt it. What the kind
of, oh, it was terrible. I asked them to stop.
I had to go back. They had to say, do you want to
do this? Do you want to do this? Do you want to do this?
Do you not want to do this? I said, fine,
I'll do it. And it was just a terrible experience.
There's just something about claustrophobia that when you
get it, you, you want to hit the eject
button and just get out of there so fast.
Yeah. Yeah. I went.
It's a strange kind of pain. It's a
strange kind of suffering. It's more suffering than pain.
Yeah. And it's so mental, right? Cause you would
have known the rational part of your brain knows
this is, this is an MRI scanner. Like this is
not going to collapse and crush me. It's not going to
harm me. It's doing me good. Many thousands
of people have been here before me, but yeah,
I once thought about when I was writing
undone, I thought about getting a business card, which
just read, I do these things. So you don't have
to say kind of, but, um, yeah, yeah. The underworld,
I haven't been back into the underworld much since
I surfaced in, in about 2018, I must say,
whereas rivers I'm going to, they're going
to flow on through my life forever.
Nice. I want to do kind of a fire round.
I want to ask you about language from different cultures
and what we can learn, learn from that.
So I'll start with old English.
Okay. Old English used to be known as
Anglo-Saxon, now old English. Uh, the, so the kenning,
a kenning is a beautiful trope of old
English, which is where you hyphenate two words together
to make a metaphoric version of another. So
bone cage, bone cage hyphenated means the skeleton,
the body. Whale road is the sea,
the sea that the, that the, that
for example, the ship sail on is that is
the whale road that, that, that becomes the sea.
And they, um, this profusion of kennings,
which is so characteristic is just a beautiful
metaphoric generosity, sort of fusing two bits
of language together. And once you start to
play with kennings, it's very, it's very hard to,
uh, to, to not play with them as a spell.
I, Kingfisher's Spell I wrote, which begins something like,
like flame, flicker, light bringer,
rivers, quiver, something like this, da-da-da-da-da.
So they're all hyphenated.
So there's Old English, the kenning is so strong.
And also in Middle English, so Gawain
and the Green Knight, for example, 14th century
great epic poem of travel and nature.
Alliteration and rhythm are absolutely central to that.
The so-called the axe knocks of the stress.
And I've learned so much from
that alliterative tradition of Old English.
The poems like the Seafarer, Gawain and
the Green Knight, really, really strong for me.
So alliteration and kennings.
Hebridean Gaelic.
Well, compressive precision, I suppose.
We've talked about Runachmoham, the shadows cast
by clouds on moorland on a sunny windy
day, many versions of that.
And also what's sometimes called GPS.
GPS.
It's the Gaelic positioning system.
What's that?
Well, place sensitivity is so coded
into a lot of Gaelic place names.
So for example, I'm a mountaineer and this
is not Hebridean Gaelic, but Gaelic and Norse
together.
So you can tell the shape of mountains
depending on the names before you see them.
So for example, a bend like Ben Nevis or
Ben Mor will be a, that's like a generic hill
will tend to be quite rounded.
Stob, Stobinian, for example, will be a sharper peak.
Skur, Skurnangilien means literally a scarier tooth.
That will typically be a very sharp peak.
So, or Ben Kruycken means the hill of
the forge, and it's actually shaped like a big
kind of forge building.
So coded into Gaelic place names are descriptors.
So the Gaelic positioning system, GPS, if
you can understand the place names, you can
kind of read the landscape with them and locate yourself.
Man.
It really gives you an extra sense of the landscape.
Yeah.
And it gives you an extra
vision into the natural world, these words.
Yeah.
And they go, you know, way, way, way, way back.
So yeah.
Yeah.
So Buccal Etiv Mor literally means the big
shepherd of the glen, the valley of Etiv.
So Mor is big, Buccal is
the shepherd, and Etiv is the valley.
And that stands like a kind of guard peak
at the head of this incredible glen of Etiv.
So Buccal Etiv.
Mor.
How about the Irish versus the English?
What are the similarities, the differences?
I think what's shared is an absolute relish
for what Heaney calls the palp and heft of
language.
The palp and the heft of language.
So palp as in palpable, like the feel of
it, the texture of words, the way, and then heft,
how they weigh in the hand.
So what does Heaney say?
What a turn of phrase.
Oh, he just, he just did that all the time.
I mean, no one taught me.
He says, keep your mind clear
as the bleb of an icicle.
And the bleb, it turns out, is not the icicle.
It's that single droplet of water that melts down
and then hangs at the end of the icicle
and then drips off.
But when it's hanging there, it's the bleb.
And the clarity of that, but also the way
it shapes the world when you look into it,
that's what Heaney's talking about.
Keep your mind clear as the bleb of the icicle.
Hmm.
So, I think that's a really good answer.
I think that's a really good answer.
Hmm.
How about English writing?
Well, I mean, where to start and where
to stop, it's the water I swim in.
I think sometimes you want language,
English, to be transparent as glass.
You don't want the reader to see anything
between them and what it is they think they
are living with you.
And sometimes you want it to
be opaque and thick and rich.
And, and, and, and...
Yeah.
...and full of pulp and heft and for the
reader to feel each word and to weigh language and
to feel language.
If you get that wrong, it's a tremendous interference.
The reader feels like they're wading
through, you know, through, through, through heavy,
heavy water, and they're being weighed
down by the heft of language.
And they, they just want to get away.
But if you get it right, it becomes
almost a physical set of performances of lifting,
feel the body's resistance to, to ideas.
to word to language and the minds leaning
towards it or moving away from it. And so,
yeah, making the reader dance with palp and with
heft can be wonderful for writer and for reader,
but other times you want them
to forget language is there entirely.
What do you make of the early 20th
century writing advice about removing needless words? Remove it,
remove it, get simple, get down to the essence. It
just seems to be the antithesis of what you do.
So, what is going on? When is that true? When
is that not true? Is that just, no, that's bad
advice. How do you feel about that? So,
Walter Pater, who was one of the great Victorian,
he says, one of the great
Victorian kind of essayists, he said,
burn with a hard and gem-like flame. He says,
I want to burn with a hard and gem-like flame.
And I think he, much earlier than Hemingway
and others, and later Raymond Carver, we could call
them like the subtractionists, the people for whom taking
away is almost always the right thing to do
with language. I think Pater and burning with
a hard gem-like flame is thinking about something
similar. Sometimes I think that's really
important. And you heard the verbalist sentences
earlier. It's like, I mean, they're not Hemingway
or Carverian, but they are gem-like. There's a
facetedness to them and they're just like, boonk, boonk,
boonk. Each of them is a sort of lapidary
image. And I don't try and connect them
or causally relate them. It's just image, image,
image, image. And to change the form, it's like
flashing those up on the mind's screen. It's like
a kind of brain cinema. There's a vividness
to that. But then adding, yeah, I'm not a
subtractionist, except at times. But yeah,
I'm not a subtractionist. Except at times.
But other, I mean, I just think
each landscape, each encounter asks a different bespoke
presence of language. And sometimes you take
away and sometimes you add. Yeah, that's,
so I just think you just judge where
you are and what you're trying to do.
We've talked a lot about making writing vivid. And
I want to go deeper on that of capturing
astonishment.
Yeah.
Of not exaggerating, like we're not trying to
exaggerate this, but also we're not trying to
diminish the astonishment that you feel. How do
you do that? How do you think about
capturing the truth of that?
I think what you say about exaggeration is a
really helpful note. And to writers and to myself,
you know, hyperbole is your enemy. Straining too
hard is your enemy. I mean, that way,
purple prose lies, I think. So,
so finding exactly the urge with astonishment is
to render it with a similar kind of extravagant
vivacity of language. And actually that can leave a
hollowness and a falsity to it, I think. So,
again, I think, so resisting the impulse
to explain astonishment, I think is important.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
The unknowables that I experience, that I've
had in my 22 years of writing, including
a ghostly encounter on a hilltop in England, sleeping
out alone on my own in a, as I
subsequently found out, a hilltop wood that
has a long history of hauntology and spectral
encounters. I didn't know any of that at the time.
How about that?
But how do you, that's an astonishment. But how do
you, how, how do you, how do you know about that?
It's a question that I've been having since I was
a student. I can't remember how long ago, but I'm
not sure.
It's a question I've been having since I was a
student. I can't remember how long ago, but I'm not sure.
How do you write it?
Well, I just try almost phenomenally
to adjust the empirical basis of it.
Just tell it how you felt it,
and we're back to not representation,
but the representation of perception.
And let the reader,
and maybe this is where subtraction becomes important,
because when you don't try to say everything
or over-lard everything with language,
the reader becomes a participant.
They are co-creating with you.
They're filling in gaps.
So letting things drop out that feel vital to you,
and again, don't over-explain,
and maybe this is where lyric writing is helpful.
Letting sense and cause drop out,
because then the reader steps in
and kind of fills those gaps and becomes your co-writer.
Yeah, I think sometimes if you have sentences
where you dot the I's, you cross the T's,
you make the edges kind of right angles, 90 degrees.
Yes, it's really well put.
You
omit the space for a reader to contemplate it,
to stir on that sentence on their own.
And I think that a lot of my gripe with,
hey, focus on clarity,
be really clear on what you're saying,
is a lot of good writing is you're gifting somebody
a turn of phrase or a sentence
that they can actually think about for a long time.
And in order for that to be a fruitful experience,
the sentence has to contain some mystery.
And I think that's a really important part of this.
Yeah.
And that's the only way
that it can be a send-off
for somebody else to make their own.
Absolutely, absolutely.
And even when one is working with a single sentence,
so I think there's a sentence in,
"'Is a river alive?'
In English, there is no verb to river,
but what could be more
of a verb than a river?"
Now, in a sense, that's a finished thought,
but in another, it is a send-off.
It's like, hold on, so what does that, oh, right.
Yeah, we don't talk about rivering this or being rivered.
But of course, is a river a verb?
Yeah, how do we translate?
So yes, again, we're back to the portal.
It's like you lend initial assent to the idea
and then it kind of complexifies in retrospect.
Yeah.
Hey, this was wonderful.
Holy cow.
We're only just embarked on the river.
We've got another three hours downstream of us.
No, I'm only kidding.
That was a crazy conversation.
Wow, it's so cool to
talk to someone who loves language
as much as we do.
Two nerds wigging out.
That is what just happened.
Wigging out.
Thank you, David.
It was a total pleasure.
Yeah.
Brilliant.
You know, I have a gripe with that word.
Oh, go on.
Let's end the wig out with a gripe.
So this is my gripe.
So in America, we overstate everything.
Yes.
We overstate everything.
And the English, very understated, okay?
And so like, no, it's pretty good.
It ain't, it's not.
It's not.
It's not in like English, English.
It's like, wow, that was actually great.
But there's one word.
That we overuse.
That the English overstate, not the Americans.
And it's brilliant.
I get out of a taxi in London.
I say, hey, thank you.
They say, oh, brilliant.
I'm like, it wasn't brilliant at all.
This was the most mundane, the most mundane,
like basic thing.
And that's my gripe with the word brilliant,
specifically with English people.
Thank you.
I consider myself chastised.
It's a, well, it's, if you swap it,
because it's a word of light, right?
Brilliant means radiant.
But if you swap it with radiant,
then you realize how silly it sounds.
Like if I'd got a,
you got out of a taxi
and the taxi driver said, that was radiant.
But no, we've fully naturalized brilliant.
But this was brilliant.
This was brilliant.
American brilliant or English brilliant?
English brilliant.
It's an exercise for the listener.
All right.
That was good fun.
Cool. Thanks.